We pick up
on today's דף daf is 90 is צדי, Tzadi, but we pick
up on פט עמוד ב. Pe-Tet Amud Bet. Before we do, I
want to read a quick תוספות Tosfos because yesterday we had discussed
the point about what do you call it, about that if you
sell a שטר, shtar, a שטר, shtar, you can be מוחל mochel
it. So I owe Michael through the שטר shtar 1,000 dollars,
and I'm not so sure I'm going to be able to collect
and anyway it's three months off, so Michael's willing to buy it
for 500 dollars. Big business about buying debt, you know, comes point
credit card debt, bank buys debt. Anyway, Michael goes to collect to
Charlie, but before he does, I say Charlie, give me 100 bucks.
Charlie gives me 100 bucks and I said I'm מוחל mochel it
to you. And שמואל Shmuel said okay now Michael can't collect because
ultimately he's collecting through me. So obviously as you can imagine that
would sort of destroy the entire market. Okay, so
תוספות Tosfos deals with this and he says like this:
we are at the תוספות Tosfos at the top of פט עמוד
ב, Pe-Tet Amud Bet, it's the middle of תוספות, Tosfos, not where
the דיבור המתחיל dibbur hamas'chil is on the previous page. Okay, ואם
תאמר,
v'im
tomar, says תוספות, Tosfos, it's the fourth line from the top, the
first wide line, people see that? Yeah. Okay, ואם תאמר, v'im tomar,
says תוספות, Tosfos, כיון דכל גברא לגבי בעלה ודאי מחלה, kivun d'chol
gavra legabei ba'ala vadai machala,
since we said that a woman would ודאי vadai be מוחל mochel
if she was selling her כתובה ketubah because she would be מוחל
mochel it for her husband's sake that he wouldn't have to pay,
so מאי קאמר לעיל אומדים כמה אדם רוצה ליתן בכתובתה של זו,
mai kama le'ail omdim kama adam rotze litein biksubah shel zo, why
like when it says oh you assess how much somebody would buy
the כתובה ketubah for? שום אדם לא יקנה אותה, shum adam lo
yikneh osah, nobody would be stupid enough to buy it. כיון דודאי
מחלה, kivun d'vadai machala, since she'll definitely be מוחל mochel it, ויכולין
עדים לומר מאי הפסדנוך, v'yecholin eidim lomar mai hifsadnuch, as it says
above, if you say the husband... okay we won't worry about that.
ויש לומר דהכא יכולה לעשות קיום במשכנות. v'yeish lomar de-hacha yechola la'asos
kiyum bemashkonot. Here's the way you could sell a debt without it
being voided. You could give somebody a משכון. mashkon.
So basically I sell Michael the debt and I guess I give
him collateral that were I to be מוחל mochel it, he could
just take the collateral instead. Something like that. או באריבות, o ba'arevut,
or there's a cosigner, או בנדר או בשבועה, o b'neder o b'shvua,
use something external to make it sure that I'm not going to
be מוחל. mochel. The exact mechanism of the נדר neder and שבועה
shvua is easy, I make a שבועה shvua I won't be מוחל.
mochel. The exact mechanism of the אריבות arevut and the משכנות mashkonot
he doesn't spell out, but שלא תמחול. shelo timchol. אבל כאן יש
לשאול למה אין משביעין אותה לעשות לו קיום וצריך עיון. aval kan
yeish lishol lama ein mashbi'in osah la'asos lo kiyum v'tzarich iyun. Okay
so you know he then wonders just why in our case doesn't
it say tell the woman to sell the כתובה ketubah and do
one of these things, do a שבועה, shvua, do a נדר neder
and so on. But basically anyway תוספות Tosfos is clearly aware of
the problem and the fact that he throws out these ideas, משכון,
mashkon, אריבות, arevut, שבועה, shvua, נדר, neder, sounds like he's also talking
about some type of a contemporary phenomenon about ways that they would
you know enforce this or make sure that people would not be
מוחל. mochel. Anyway I just thought that was very interesting. That's historically
significant because the modern financial system would be hundreds of years after
תוספות. Tosfos. תוספות Tosfos realizes this problem back in the Middle Ages.
Right, I mean all what do you call it, all you know
money, the whole the whole bit, the ability to have well you
know this goes back to the nights but the whole way you
know you're able to have currency in its significant sense is because
you're able to deal with these things about the debt. Okay, anyway,
so let's continue in the גמרא. Gemara. So again today's דף daf
is דף צדי Daf Tzadi and we pick up on the bottom
of פט עמוד ב Pe-Tet Amud Bet and we are discussing the
issue of תקנת אושא. Takanas Usha. תקנת אושא, Takanas Usha, there was
a claim, there's a question about a woman who sold her כתובה
ketubah and to her son, or gifted her כתובה ketubah to her
son. Now you could do about selling her כתובה ketubah and does
that work? Because here she owns her נכסי מלוג, Nichsei Milug, the
husband eats פירות. peiros. Since she has the title, is she able
to transfer that title? And the גמרא Gemara said if you say
קנין פירות לאו כקנין הגוף דמי, Kinyan Peiros lav keKinyan haGuf dami,
the husband's owning the פירות, peiros, it does not give him a
type of ownership over this, then in principle she would be able
to sell it. But תקנת אושא, Takanas Usha, there was a claim
that there was a תקנה takana in אושא Usha which was soon
after כרם ביבנה Kerem beYavneh that a husband had greater rights to
the property than he technically deserved, and that would block the wife
from selling her נכסי מלוג. Nichsei Milug. But that had been not
so clear that everybody agrees that that תקנה takana exists and that's
what the גמרא Gemara is now going to turn to. So let's
take a look. The גמרא Gemara says like this, לימא תקנת אושא
תנאי, lema Takanas Usha Tanna'ei, let's say this question of whether there
is this תקנת אושא Takanas Usha is a debate of תנאים. Tanna'im.
דתני חדא, detani chada, we taught in one ברייתא, braita, עבדי מלוג
יוצאין בשן ועין. avdei milug yotzin b'shein v'ayin. Let's say this is
not a piece of land, let's say this עבד eved comes in
and she has title to... to are slaves. Okay? So she has
title to slaves and he eats the פירות. peiros. What does it
mean that he eats the פירות? peiros? They work for him. They
work for him, but they're her slaves. Okay, that's a נכסי מלוג.
nichsei milog. Now, one of them knocks out the slave's eye or
tooth. Does the slave go free? So the question is, who is
the slave's master? Okay, so let's take a look. דתניא חדא, Detanya
chada, we have one ברייתא braisa teaches: עבדי מלוג יוצאים בשן ועין
לאשה. avdei milog yotzin b'shein v'ayin l'isha. That if the woman knocks
out the eye it goes free. אבל לא לאיש, Aval lo l'ish,
טעמא, ta'ama, that would mean the woman is considered the owner. דתניא
אידך, Detanya idach, we have another ברייתא: braisa: לא לאיש ולא לאשה,
lo l'ish v'lo l'isha, neither the man or the woman. So that's
a great arrangement you can do to get out of this whole
הלכה halacha of שן ועין, shein v'ayin, although you could always just
admit it or something.
Anyway,
but okay. סברוה, Savruha, now what's this space? We assume דכולי עלמא
קניין פירות לאו כקניין הגוף דמי. de'kulei alma kinyan peiros lav k'kinyan
haguf dami. Everybody agrees with ריש לקיש Reish Lakish that the right
to פירות peiros by itself does not make you like an owner.
So we start with the idea that the husband is not the
owner because קניין פירות kinyan peiros is not enough. So then, what's
the issue? מאי לאו בהא קמיפלגי, Mai lav b'hai kamifligi, it must
be this is what they debate: דמאן דאמר לאשה, de'man d'amar l'isha,
the woman is considered the owner, so לית ליה תקנת אושא. lais
lei takanas Usha. He doesn't hold of תקנת אושא. takanas Usha. Woman
has the title, husband has the פירות, peiros, פירות peiros aren't enough,
woman is the owner, when she knocks out the eye it goes
free, but not the husband. Okay? ומאן דאמר לא לאיש ולא לאשה,
U'man d'amar lo l'ish v'lo l'isha, the one that says not the
husband or the wife, אית ליה תקנת אושא. is lei takanas Usha.
He holds of תקנת אושא. takanas Usha. Now תקנת אושא takanas Usha
doesn't make the husband the owner and not the woman. We start
with the idea that the woman is fundamentally the owner. The husband
has קניין פירות. kinyan peiros. תקנת אושא takanas Usha gives the husband
more power. Now then, you'd have to ask the question: Does it
give him like blocking and veto power, and you know, does it
make him an equal owner to the wife? It seems here that
the תקנת אושא takanas Usha would be more what it is able
to do to prevent the wife than what it does to empower
him. Because otherwise you could say why doesn't it go free for
either of them? You know, but the point is, no, it doesn't
go free for the wife, because anyway if you think about it
in this way as well, going out free is, you know, could
be thought of similarly to like selling. If you have the ability
to change the status, to give it away? So if you say
תקנת אושא, takanas Usha, the wife doesn't have the ability to give
him away because the husband can block it. The husband doesn't have
the ability to give the slave away because the wife has title.
So basically if neither of them can give it away, neither of
them can set it free. Okay, so that presumably that is the
debate. And if it's just the wife, it means the husband can't
block it and you don't hold of תקנת אושא. takanas Usha. Okay,
so the גמרא Gemara says, isn't that what they're debating? So there
are too many, there are too many, you know, factors here to
nail down what the debate is. So the גמרא Gemara is going
to deal with some other possibilities. לא, דכולי עלמא אית להו תקנת
אושא. Lo, de'kulei alma is lehu takanas Usha. No, no, everybody holds
of תקנת אושא. takanas Usha. So then why would the wife be
able to set the slave free by knocking out the eye or
the tooth? אלא כאן קודם תקנה כאן לאחר תקנה. Ela kan kodem
takana kan l'achar takana. Maybe one of these ברייתות braisos was taught
before the תקנה. takana. ואיבעית אימא, V'iba'is eima, or I can tell
you, אידי ואידי לאחר תקנה. idi v'idi l'achar takana. They both, it's
after the תקנה. takana. ואית להו תקנת אושא, V'is lehu takanas Usha,
and you hold of תקנת אושא. takanas Usha. So if the husband
can block the wife from selling, why could the wife, by knocking
out the eye or the tooth, make the slave go free? So
אלא למאן דאמר לאשה ולא לאיש, ela l'man d'amar l'isha v'lo l'ish,
the one that says for the woman and not the man, that
she can even though he could block her from selling,
מאי טעמא, mai ta'ama, what's the reason? כדרבא, K'de'Rava, like רבא Rava
would say. דאמר רבא: De'amar Rava: הקדש חמץ ושחרור מפקיעין מידי שעבוד.
hekdesh chametz v'shichrur mafki'in midei shibud.
That if you sanctify something or it becomes חמץ chametz and becomes
אסור בהנאה, assur b'hana'ah, or you
free
a slave, that undoes a lien. Which basically means the following: Michael
here has a lien on my slave. No, not the other way
around. We'll start with הקדש. hekdesh. He's got a lien on my
on my cow. Now normally you don't have liens on cattle, but
I can give him an אפותיקי, apoteiki, I give him a lien
on my cow.
If I sanctify the cow as בדק הבית, bedek habayis, I donate
it to the Temple treasury, Michael can take it out of the
Temple treasury. It's just like that's fundamentally about transferring ownership. We've discussed
this before. So the same way if I sold it to, you
know, to Dov, Michael can take it away from Dov. If I
sold it to the Temple or gave it to the Temple, Michael
can take it away from the Temple. But if I am מקדיש
makdish it as a קרבן, korban, remember we've discussed this, that's not
fundamentally about changing ownership. That's about changing its identity. It is now
something that is different. It is now a sanctified object. It's now
an עולה, olah, right? There's something about its status that has fundamentally
changed. It might not even be owned by the בית המקדש, Beis
Hamikdash, but it's a different type of a thing. Okay? And so
in that case, basically, that new status is not something that now
Michael can now take, okay? Because it's a completely new identity. And
the same is true, the more easier example would be, well let's
say חמץ. chametz. Now of course the question by חמץ chametz is
where do you have a lien on חמץ chametz and so on.
A non-Jew has a lien on my חמץ chametz and I keep
it in my house over פסח Pesach and it becomes
In that case, once it changes that status and becomes something אסור
בהנאה, assur behana'ah, it's a status change, he cannot go ahead and
now take it because it's fundamentally a different object. Now one way
of understanding this the way the ירושלמי Yerushalmi says it, you could
just say נשתנה, nishtana, it's a fundamentally different type of a thing,
it's you know, it's transformed so the שיעבוד shibud goes away. But
the ירושלמי Yerushalmi also says that like, you know, at least in
the case of like הקדש, hekdesh, it wouldn't be true by אסור
בהנאה assur behana'ah because the חמץ chametz isn't אסור בהנאה assur behana'ah
to the non-Jew. But in the case of הקדש, hekdesh, if Michael
takes the cow, right, then it would fundamentally be that he's asserting
his ownership, which would basically mean that the הקדש hekdesh status would
have to go away, but something can't become הקדש hekdesh and then
קרבן הקדש korban hekdesh and then magically stop being a קרבן. korban.
Okay, but it's not necessarily limited to that. The fundamental idea is
that there's a change of status. Okay, similarly freeing the slave. If
Michael has a lien on my slaves and I free them, they
become now בני חורין. bnei chorin. How can he now go ahead
and take a somebody who's now a freeman and take him and
make him into a slave? That's, you know, or you know, that's
the biggest change of status, the biggest thing that is obvious that
his asserting his lien would be meaningless at that point.
And then how did they do it in the Canaanite to begin
with? They took free people and made them slaves.
Yeah, after they conquered the nation in battle or something like that.
But this person that now is a Jew and is free, what
are you gonna do? You're gonna go ahead and conquer them in
battle?
You can't just assert your lien and turn his status. Okay, so
even though you're distinguishing between ownership and identity, they're they're linked with
each other.
Well, when it changes identity, any no longer שיעבוד shibud ownership issues
go away, right. So therefore what the גמרא Gemara is saying is,
since the woman has title, now this is the part of the
thing though, because if a random person or the husband knocked out
the eye or the tooth, you wouldn't say the שחרור shichrur is
מפקיע mafki'a מידי שיעבוד midei shibud of the woman. You have to
fundamentally start with your role as the owner of the slave, which
the woman is, the husband is not. She starts with her role
as the owner of the slave, she knocks out the eye or
the tooth, the הלכה halacha is the slave goes free. Husband says
no, I'm blocking it because I have liens, like she could block
a sale. So he says no, sorry you can't block it, this
is a fundamental change of status, it's not just a sale. And
therefore when the slave now becomes a free person, your liens, your
rights don't have the right to block that to block that from
happening. Okay, so now so that's the reason that it could be
the wife even after תקנת אושא. takanat Usha.
Wait, so so the dead the injury is co-terminous with the shift
in identity of the עבד. eved. Right. The moment the eye is
knocked out, he's no longer עבד, eved, he's a free person.
Correct, that is correct.
So רבא's Rava point is it's a sort of a מחלוקת machlokes
there?
Well, that's what the גמרא's Gemara going to say. So לימא דרבא
תנאי היא? leima de-Rava tanna'ei hi? So would that mean that רבא
Rava would have to concede that his position is a debate of
תנאים? Tannaim? If everybody agrees it's after תקנת אושא takanat Usha and
one says the wife can set him free because of this whole
idea of שחרור shichrur change, you know, you know making the husband's
lien irrelevant,
what does the other one hold? Presumably the other one disagrees with
רבא. Rava. The גמרא Gemara says לא, lo, no, כולי עלמא אית
להו דרבא, kulei alma it lehu de-Rava, everybody could agree with רבא.
Rava. והכא אמור רבנן לשיעבודא דבעל, vehacha amur rabanan lishibuda de-ba'al, here
the question is maybe the rabbis made the husband's liens so strong
that they made him like an owner, not just like a lien
but like an actual partial owner. Okay, and so much so that
what the wife does would not... Now let's say you have two
partners and one of them knocks out the eye, right? What happens
there? Does he go free or not go free? You know, so
you'd have to understand the exact mechanism that he's not just a
lien, he's an owner and enough of an owner to block the
to block the wife. I don't know, I have to check that.
Okay, so that's homework for the student. Okay, ואיבעית אימא, ve-i ba'it
eima, and if you want I can say, כולי עלמא לית להו
להני תנאי תקנת אושא, kulei alma leit lehu lehani tanna'ei takanat Usha,
here's another way of explaining the debate. None of these תנאים Tannaim
hold of תקנת אושא. takanat Usha. לית להו להני תנאי תקנת אושא.
leit lehu lehani tanna'ei takanat Usha. והכא בקניין פירות כקניין הגוף דמי
פליגי, vehacha be-kinyan perot kekinyan haguf dami pligi,
and here the debate is the old רבי יוחנן וריש לקיש Rabbi
Yochanan ve-Reish Lakish debate. Okay, every forget תקנת אושא, takanat Usha, there's
no אושא. Usha. So she has title, so she should be able
to sell or she should be able to free the slaves. But
he has קניין פירות, kinyan perot, so what would block it? Not
תקנת אושא, takanat Usha, but let's take a look. Okay, what what
would block it? Not the תקנת אושא, takanat Usha, but what would
block it would be a position of קניין פירות כקניין הגוף דמי.
kinyan perot kekinyan haguf dami. That the קניין פירות kinyan perot makes
him like an owner. So תקנת אושא takanat Usha is needed if
you hold like ריש לקיש Reish Lakish that קניין פירות לאו כקניין
הגוף דמי. kinyan perot lav kekinyan haguf dami. But if you hold
like רבי יוחנן, Rabbi Yochanan, you already have the right to block.
Exactly, exactly. Okay. So the גמרא Gemara says בקניין פירות כקניין הגוף
דמי פליגי. be-kinyan perot kekinyan haguf dami pligi. ובפלוגתא דהני תנאים. uve-plugta
de-hani tannaim. Now
okay, and so that's another way of explaining it. Now this debate
of this question of the slave going free and who knocked out
the eye etc. parallels this following debate of תנאים. Tannaim. Let's take
a look. דתניא, detanya, we taught in a ברייתא, braita, המוכר עבדו
לאחר ופסק עמו על מנת שישמשנו שלושים יום. hamocher avdo le-acher ufaska
imo al menat she-yeshameshenu shloshim yom. I sell my slave to Michael
and I say but he's going to but he'll work for me
for the first thirty days. You own him now, but I'll get
the... So I have, what do I have? קניין הפירות Kinyan haperos
for thirty days over this slave. Okay, here’s going to be the
question. רבי יוסי סבר אומר שניהם ישנן בדין יום או יומיים. Rabbi
Yossi savar omer shneyhem yeshnan bedin yom o yomayim.
This is not the question of the slave going free, this is
the question of, you know, which might be connected to the ability
to sell the slave without the other one blocking it. This is
the question that if a master beats his slave,
I skipped a bunch of lines.
I’m sorry. Okay, sorry, sorry, sorry. Okay, where are we? המוכר עבדו
לאחר ופסק עמו על מנת שישמשנו שלושים יום. Hamocher avdo leachar upasak
imo al menas sheyishmeshunu shloshim yom. רבי מאיר אומר מי שישנו בדין
יום או יומיים. Rabbi Meir omer mi sheyeshno bedin yom o yomayim.
Yeah, מפני שתחתיו. mipnei shetachasav.
So the question here is, thank you, not going free, but the
הלכה halacha in the תורה, Torah, the תורה Torah says, again, this
is such a radical sort of, you know, חידוש chiddush of the
תורה, Torah, that while not changing the deep-seated institution of slaves as
property, you know, also recognizes them as human beings and would say
that a master who so harshly beats his slave that he dies
within a day or two, the master is put to death. Okay,
which is crazy, like you would never have heard about that in
ancient society. So that’s the הלכה halacha of יום או יומיים. yom
o yomayim. It says a day or two. What does that mean
a day or two? Like which one is it? But okay, that’s
our הלכה halacha right now. But the point is that who is
the master? Right?
Now here, if some stranger beats the slave and he dies five
days later, that person is put to death. It’s only the master
that is given, like this idea that if it takes more than
a day or two, well, you did have a right to beat
him, you were the master, so if it was more than a
day or two, we would say it was not an overly vicious
beating and therefore you’re not liable to death penalty. But some stranger
who beats him, if it was so bad that he died within
five days or whatever, you know, now of course the question is,
was he trying to kill him, question about כוונה, kavana, do you
execute somebody for, you know, for when it was a likely outcome
but not intended or not a definite outcome, again, we’re not going
to worry about that. The basic point though is that the master
gets off if it takes more than a day or two. Okay,
because he fundamentally had a right to, you know, to beat his
slave. This is the reality of the institution. So the question is:
who is the master? One person has the right, has the פירות
peros for thirty days. He’s working for ראובן Reuven for thirty days,
but שמעון Shimon holds title.
Right? Which one is the master if he beats him and dies,
and if it took more than one or two days, the person
would get off? So let’s take a look. Okay, so רבי מאיר
אומר ראשון ישנו בדין יום או יומיים, Rabbi Meir omer rishon yeshno
bedin yom o yomayim, the first guy, he’s
the only one,
the only the first guy he’s working for, מפני שתחתיו, mipnei shetachasav,
because he’s directly under his control. Okay, now you could have just
said based on the logic I did that has nothing to do
with קניין פירות. kinyan peros. This has to do with the idea
that if he’s working for me, I have the right to beat
him. Michael might have title but he’s not yet working for Michael,
why does Michael have the right to beat him? Right? You could
have made it tactical in that sense. But the גמרא Gemara doesn’t.
The גמרא Gemara makes it formal. The גמרא Gemara says like this.
Okay, מפני שתחתיו, mipnei shetachasav, קסבר קניין פירות כקניין הגוף דמי. kasavar
kinyan peros kekinyan haguf dami.
The קניין הפירות kinyan haperos that ראובן Reuven has over him is
like a קניין הגוף. kinyan haguf. And this is, by the way,
more than we’ve considered before. He’s a קניין הגוף kinyan haguf more
than the person that has title, right? The guy he’s working for
is the master, and the guy who has title is not considered
the master. So this is a more extreme version of קניין פירות
כקניין הגוף דמי. kinyan peros kekinyan haguf dami. מפני שתחתיו. mipnei shetachasav.
Okay, רבי יהודה אומר שני ישנו בדין יום או יומיים. Rabbi Yehuda
omer sheni yeshno bedin yom o yomayim.
No,
it’s the guy who has title. He is considered the master. מפני
שהוא כספו, mipnei shehu kaspo, because he’s the one who owns him,
which is a way of saying he has title. קסבר קניין פירות
לאו כקניין הגוף דמי. kasavar kinyan peros lav kekinyan haguf dami. The
קניין הפירות kinyan haperos does not make ראובן Reuven the owner. שמעון
Shimon has title, שמעון Shimon is considered the owner. So here it’s
either all ראובן Reuven or all שמעון. Shimon. רבי יוסי אומר שניהם
ישנן בדין יום או יומיים. Rabbi Yossi omer shneyhem yeshnan bedin yom
o yomayim. They’re both owners. זה מפני שתחתיו וזה מפני שהוא כספו.
zeh mipnei shetachasav vezeh mipnei shehu kaspo. Now
I would have said that קניין פירות kinyan peros is כקניין הגוף
kekinyan haguf and you have two people that have a קניין הגוף,
kinyan haguf, the guy with the title and the guy with the
rights. But the גמרא Gemara frames it differently. The גמרא Gemara says
מספקא ליה, mesapka leh, he’s uncertain. קניין פירות אי כקניין הגוף דמי
אי לאו כקניין הגוף דמי. kinyan peros i kekinyan haguf dami i
lav kekinyan haguf dami. Is it like קניין הגוף kinyan haguf or
not? מספקא ליה, mesapka leh, so we don’t know which one is
the master. And since we don’t know which one is the master,
we’re not going to execute either of them. Okay, now what? בדין
יום או יומיים bedin yom o yomayim gets the master off if
the slave lasts longer. Now, again,
it’s interesting from yesterday, קניין הפירות kinyan haperos seemed like it was
only strong enough to maybe allow for a block. It was strong
enough to make me maybe an equal owner. Here, the גמרא Gemara
is dealing with קניין הפירות kinyan haperos if it’s כקניין הגוף kekinyan
haguf makes you the only owner. So the only way the גמרא
Gemara can understand רבי יוסי Rabbi Yossi is by saying he has
a ספק. safek. It’s not willing to consider that קניין פירות kinyan
peros is an equal owner to the קניין הגוף. kinyan haguf. Okay,
so that’s רבי יוסי. Rabbi Yossi.
רבי אליעזר אמר, Rebbi Eliezer amar, there are four possibilities here. Okay,
we're going to cover all four of them:
A or B, A and B, neither A or B. רבי אליעזר
אומר שניהם אינם בדין יום או יומיים, Rebbi Eliezer omer sheneihem einam
badin yom o yomayim, neither. זה לפי שאינו תחתיו, zeh lefi she'eino
tachasav, the guy who has title says he's not working for him,
וזה לפי שאינו כספו, vezeh lefi she'eino kaspo, and the other one
is because he doesn't own him. So you basically need both. In
order to be considered the master, you need title and he has
to work for you. So how does this fit into our קניין
פירות? Kinyan Peros? Again, you could have made this debate completely local,
completely just about this issue of יום או יומיים. Yom o Yomayim.
The גמרא's Gemara making it part of a more global question. So
what's this about? So אמר רבא מאי טעמא דרבי אליעזר? amar Rava
mai ta'ama deRebbi Eliezer? So the only way we can explain רבי
אליעזר Rebbi Eliezer is to make it a local concern because again,
by the קניין פירות Kinyan Peros issue, if it can either be
all A or all B or a doubt which gives it to
A and B, like how do you explain neither A nor B?
So for this, we have to say it's a special local הלכה.
halacha. Okay, מאי טעמא דרבי אליעזר אמר קרא, mai ta'ama deRebbi Eliezer
amar kra, the verse says כי כספו הוא, ki chaspo hu, לא
יוקם, lo yukam, the master will not be... the slave will not
be avenged because the slave ultimately was the master's property, כי כספו
הוא. ki chaspo hu.
כספו כספו, kaspo kaspo, his property, and then the extra word הוא,
hu, ליז כספו המיוחד לו, liz kaspo hamyuchad lo, something that is
fully his property. So therefore it only applies to something that he
has title to and it's an active and meaningful title that he
actually is working for. You know, the other day the Marli pointed
this out that some of these issues parallel and in particular this
one, the teaching of רבי יוחנן Rebbi Yochanan earlier about, you know,
a גזלן, gazlan, you know, can't be... and if a גזלן gazlan
steals something, he can't be מקדיש makdish and the owner can't be
מקדיש. makdish. The owner can't be מקדיש makdish because it's אינו ברשותו
eino birshuso and the גזלן gazlan because it's אינו שלו. eino shelo.
And you have to have like both, that the sense of ownership
requires both, that you own it and it be under your control.
While you know, there's something very similar to here, you could say
if one guy has קניין פירות Kinyan Peros and one guy has
קניין הגוף, Kinyan Haguf, neither of them are the owner. Okay, and
that's basically what רבא Rava says, at least for the purpose here
of slaves, of the slave in יום או יומיים, Yom o Yomayim,
whether we're going to expand that in a minute we will see.
Yes?
So would you say it's similar also let's say to a rental
agreement, right? I own the house, you're renting it from me, I
can't just come in whenever I
want and take a
chair from the house.
Right, that is correct. Now the רמב"ם Rambam actually says that what
a rental is in general is a קניין פירות לזמן. Kinyan Peros
lizman. That's what the רמב"ם Rambam says. Right, yeah. So you have
the rights of usage for a limited time. Right, so like this
case of the שלושים יום. sheloshim yom. Right, okay. Yeah.
So what's the punishment if neither of them own the slave, then
why isn't somebody just responsible as a non-owner for killing him?
They are, because neither of them have the הלכה halacha of יום
או יומיים. Yom o Yomayim. They would... either of them would be
executed if the slave died, even if he died many days later.
Oh,
I
just noticed the note about רבי אליעזר, Rebbi Eliezer, not about רבי
יאשיה.
Rebbi Yoshiya. What?
It says...
I mean not רבי אליעזר, Rebbi Eliezer, you're looking at the note
about רבי יוסי. Rebbi Yose. Right, רבי יוסי. Rebbi Yose. We're talking
about רבי אליעזר. Rebbi Eliezer. But in that case, they both are...
according to רבי יוסי Rebbi Yose they both are considered the master,
or each one might be the master. So if the slave lasts
more than... more than two days, the day or two, whatever, so
she goes. Yeah, okay. Thanks.
So did
the רמב"ן Ramban talk about a term of rent that is an
absurdly long time? Not...
not that I know of, and I'm not going there now. Okay.
So the גמרא Gemara says like this. Okay.
99 years. Okay.
כמאן אזלא הא דאמר אמימר, Keman azla had de'amar Ameimar, now who...
who is it going like that which אמימר Ameimar teaches? איש ואישה
שמכרו בנכסי מלוג Ish ve'ishah shemachru binichsei melog לא עשו ולא כלום.
lo asu velo klum.
So now we're going back to this idea of can you have
an idea that קניין פירות Kinyan Peros and קניין הגוף Kinyan Haguf
means neither of them are considered really fully have... have full rights
of owner. Okay? They... so... so here seems to be an אמימר's
Ameimar teaching. They jointly to try to sell הנכסי מלוג hanichsei melog
and they're not able to do it. Now רש"י Rashi says that's
different than partners. If it's partners, I own 50 percent, but I'm
a full owner over 50 percent, and Michael's a full owner of
50 percent. So I can sell my 50 percent, and he can
sell his 50 percent, and together as partners we sold our joint
plot of land. But in this case of the נכסי מלוג, nichsei
melog, okay, now Michael will be Michelle. Okay. So... so I have
title, but... but I... excuse me, I have the right of פירות,
Peros, but I can't sell it, I don't have title. He's got
title, but he can't sell it because he doesn't have פירות. Peros.
And if קניין פירות לאו כקניין הגוף, Kinyan Peros lav keKinyan Guf,
then he doesn't really have control... the control over it.
So they both come and joint...
joint on the dotted line. Between all of them. No, the way
we would have to do it is you would have to give
me your קניין פירות Kinyan Peros and then I would be able
to sell it, or I'd have to give you... I'm sorry, I'd
have to give you my קניין פירות Kinyan Peros and you would
sell it, or you'd have to give me your title and then
I would sell it. Okay. But there's no way we can both
with... there's no concept of like... creating a corporation. You're trying to
sell your part, I'm trying to sell my part, and neither of
us can sell our part alone. But even if we both sign
at the same time? Right, so what it shows you is it's
not because I can block you, it's just because objectively you don't
have enough rights. Even though you're not enough of an owner to
transfer even the thing that you own. But you don't have enough
of that status of an owner. Okay, so איזהו שמקחו נפסל ממנו
לא עשו ולא כלום. כמאן? כרבי אליעזר, Keman? K'Rabbi Eliezer, that's like
Rabbi Eliezer, that basically says that the סיפא seifa פירות קניין הגוף.
peiros kinyan haguf. Neither of them have a title of owner. Okay,
so מאן תנא להא דתנו רבנן? Man tanna l'ha d'tanu rabanan? Who
is the תנא tanna of that which we taught in the ברייתא?
baraita? מי שחציו עבד וחציו בן חורין, Mi she-chetzio eved v'chetzio ben
chorin, somebody that's half-slave, half-free, וכן עבד של שני שותפין, ve-chen eved
shel shenei shutafin, or of two partners, and because I just said
two partners is really not a problem because it says this שותפין
shutafin means essentially what we said before: one owns title and one's
own פירות. peiros. אין יוצאים בראשי איברים שאינם חוזרים. Ein yotzim b'roshei
evarim she'einam chozrim. They don't go free by the, you know, by
the knocking out of the eye. So who's that going like? Now
basically, I think I mentioned that before, right? What if you have
two partners and one of them knocked out the eye and so
on? The simple sense of this ברייתא baraita is that you have
to be 100% owner, not only qualitatively but even quantitatively. So if
he's half-free and you only own the other half, or you're a
partner and you knock out one of the eye, you only own
50%, so he does not 100% owner, he doesn't go free. So
אמר ליה רב מרדכי לאביי: הכי אמר
משמיה דרבא.
Amar lei Rav Mordechai l'Abaye: Hachi
amar mishmeih d'Rava. רבי אליעזר היא,
Rabbi
Eliezer
hi, it's like Rabbi Eliezer. מי לא אמר רבי אליעזר: 'כספו' המיוחד
לו? הכי נמי 'עבדו' המיוחד לו. So then he
makes the דרשה drasha from that פסוק: passuk: yours, it has to
be a full, here too, it has to be a full, your
slave before he goes free. Now again, this is hard because the
simple sense here is not just qualitatively you have to be a
full owner, but even quantitatively.
And that's very strange, right? So תוספות Tosafot as I said tries
to say this is also a case of קניין פירות קניין הגוף,
kinyan peiros kinyan haguf, but maybe that's why the גמרא Gemara here
again quotes a פסוק passuk and refers to a פסוק. passuk. Right?
Maybe in general, in all other areas, of course, if you're normal
שותפין, shutafin, you can sell your half, he can sell his half.
But if there's a special דרשה drasha in the פסוק, passuk, maybe
that דרשה drasha in the פסוק passuk is telling us for this
הלכה halakha of שן ועין, shein v'ayin, you have to be both
a full qualitative and full quantitative owner. And therefore, even if you
are owner of 100% of half of him, he doesn't, that half
does not go free. Okay, so that was the end of that
whole discussion of קניין פירות קניין הגוף kinyan peiros kinyan haguf and
the woman's right to sell her property. Okay, next משנה. mishna. התוקע
לחברו. Ha-tokeia l'chaveiro. Now we are moving back to discussing בושת, boshet,
okay, embarrassment or shame.
So let's take a look and what we're going to find is
interesting, it's so ironic, you know, the whole case of the payments
all are a case-by-case assessment. How much would this damage affect the
market price? How much are the doctor bills? How much would this
person be willing to take to undergo or to prevent this type
of pain and suffering? Okay, so embarrassment also, right? How much is
this person, you know, embarrassed by this thing? Now exactly how would
you assess that? I guess it would be something similar to the
suffering question: how much money would you take to undergo this embarrassment?
But that, you know, if you remember by the sufferings, although a
week I wasn't here, but you know, there's the reverse question is
how much would you pay to prevent this suffering? And there's a
lot, there's very different answers to those two, which a lot have
to also do with what your financial, you know, wherewithal. Anyway, but
okay, but it would be an assessment by the case-by-case and the
משנה mishna before said: הכל לפי המבייש והמתבייש. Hakol lefi ha-mivayesh ve-ha-mitbayesh.
It's all going based on the embarrassor and embarrassed to assess how
shameful or how embarrassing that experience was. Okay, given that, what we
find is by בושת boshet as opposed to by anything else, חז"ל
Chazal tried to set fixed amounts. Maybe because it was just too
hard to assess, okay? And so let's take a look at our
next משנה mishna again.
Yeah, well we are actually. Okay, התוקע לחברו, Ha-tokeia l'chaveiro, somebody who
basically hits his friend on the ear, נותן לו סלע, noten lo
sela, gives him a סלע, sela, which is like four זוז. zuz.
רבי יהודה אומר משום רבי יוסי הגלילי: מנה, Rabbi Yehuda omer mishum
Rabbi Yosi ha-Glili: Maneh, a hundred זוז. zuz. So to give you
some sense, right, a כתובה ketubah was 200 זוז, zuz, and the
200 זוז zuz was basically I think I read somewhere roughly the
amount it would take for
a to provide for a person for a year.
Okay, so 100 so you know, again I don't know what the
minimum wage you know if you talk about minimum wage, but let's
say now what do we say now like the poverty amount is
you know minimum wage like 20,000, 30,000 something like that?
Not even that for a minimum wage. Yeah.
Okay, so anyway, so okay, so 100 זוז zuz would be half
of that. How
does התוקע tokeia mean hitting? You're right, normally you would say it
would mean to yell into, but anyway, that's a conversation for best.
I know, I know, it's not. So anyway, okay, but again what,
you know, ר' יהודה Reb Yehuda is twenty-five times the תנא קמא.
Tanna Kamma. I'm sorry, ר'... Reb... I'm sorry, yeah, ר' יוסי... Reb
Yose... ר' יהודה Reb Yehuda in the name of ר' יוסי הגלילי
Reb Yose HaGlili is twenty-five times the תנא קמא. Tanna Kamma. I'm
sorry, ר' יהודה's Reb Yehuda a hundred times... I mean the תנא
קמא Tanna Kamma is eight hundred and ר' יהודה Reb Yehuda is
twenty thousand. So that's twenty-five times. סטרה, Sotra, if you slapped him
in the face, נותן לו מאתיים זוז, nosen lo masayim zuz, 200
זוז, zuz, okay? The full value of a כתובה, kesubah, think about
it that way for slapping somebody in the face, okay, in public
presumably. ולאחר ידו, V'le'acher yado, with the back of your hand, which
is a way of like showing like, you know, like contempt, thank
you, נותן לו ארבע מאות זוז, nosen lo arba meos zuz, 400
זוז. zuz. צרמו באוזנו, Tzarmo b'ozno, if you yank him by his
ear, okay? I had a teacher that once did that to me
in grade school. תלש בשערו, Talash b'searo, yanked me by my ear
to the principal's office. תלש בשערו, Talash b'searo, pulled his hair, I
don't mean pulled out or pulled him by the hair. רקק והגיע
בו רוקו, Rakak v'higi'a bo roko, spat at him and the spit
hit him. העביר טליתו ממנו, He'evir taliso mimenu, pulled off his cloak.
טלית Talis here does not mean a prayer shawl, pulled his cloak
off of him and then he was naked. That's not clear, presumably
he was, might have been wearing underwear or something. פרע ראש אשה
בשוק, Para rosh isha bashuk, you uncovered a woman's hair, so you're
uncovering stuff that's obviously normally covered, נותן לו ארבע מאות זוז, nosen
lo arba meos zuz, 400 זוז. zuz. I'm going to have to
go back to that teacher, I have some serious money coming to
me.
Anyway, נותן לו nosen lo just generic, נותן לו nosen lo be
דוקא davka the husband,
נותן לו nosen lo to the woman?
Yes, נותן לו nosen lo is a generic, right. זה הכלל, Ze
haklal, this is the principle, הכל לפי כבודו, hakol lefi kevodo, it
all based on the person's honor. So what does it mean? If
it's the principle you just gave me a fixed amount and then
you said oh by the way it all depends on the person's
honor. So,
גמרא Gemara tries to make sense of that. אמר רבי עקיבא, Amar
Rabbi Akiva, אפילו עניים שבישראל רואים אותם כאילו הם בני חורין שירדו
מנכסיהם שבני אברהם יצחק ויעקב. afilu aniyim sheb'yisrael ro'im osam k'ilu hem
bnei chorin she'yardu min'chaseihem shebnei Avraham Yitzchak v'Yaakov. So it seems like
רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva is trying to מתרץ metaretz these two ideas,
fixed amount and the זה הכלל. ze haklal. And רבי עקיבא Rabbi
Akiva is saying, even, who was quoted last week, even the poor
are basically, we all come from אברהם יצחק ויעקב, Avraham Yitzchak v'Yaakov,
we are all like, you know, descendants of kings and princes,
okay, like you have that nowadays, descendants of royalty. You know, they
might be, you know, they might be poor, but they're descendants of
royalty. There's a difference between, you know, class and wealth. So anyway,
so everybody comes from the upper classes, even if they're poor, they
could be the poor upper class. And therefore, and the issue about
honor is not a question of how wealthy you are, it's a
question of your social standing, okay, and you could, so that, I
mean, and that's very, you know, true. I read this book, what
was it called? The Paying Guest, which was about this case about
this like upper class family that basically had, you know, had no
money so they had to take in boarders, but you don't want
to actually say you're renting out your house so they were paying
guests. So anyway, but there's a difference between class and wealth. And
רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva says we all are from the upper classes,
so therefore everybody has a high level of בושת, boshet, you know,
a high payment. So what he's trying to do is saying these
numbers given, it seems like he's saying these numbers given in the
משנה Mishnah which are very, very high numbers, numbers you would expect
only for somebody from the upper class, how could we say that
they apply by everybody? What about הכל לפי כבודו? hakol lefi kevodo?
Yes, הכל לפי כבודו, hakol lefi kevodo, and everybody has maximum כבוד.
kavod. Yes.
I just want to, does עניים aniyim is just opposed to בני
חורין? bnei chorin? So is עניים aniyim here really mean an עבד
עברי? eved ivri? Or is it, right, no there's not parallel. It
should be עשירים, ashirim, עניים ועשירים. aniyim v'ashirim.
Yeah. So, no. So it's a good point and I think that
I'll just mention, you know, it's very interesting when we talk about
פסח, Pesach, we talk about, you know, reclining and drinking wine to
act as בני חורין, bnei chorin, free people. But what do you
mean free people? Means wealthy people, it's not free people. So actually,
you know, what we are saying here is like those often go
together, but you know, what we actually mean is people of the,
you know, upper class and that often comes with this wealth and
this type of luxurious lifestyle. But yes, that's why that you can
be a בני חורין שירדו מנכסיהם, bnei chorin she'yardu min'chaseihem, you can
be a poor free person, a poor person from the upper classes.
That's, that's exactly the point. Okay? שבני אברהם יצחק ויעקב, Shebnei Avraham
Yitzchak v'Yaakov, says רבי עקיבא, Rabbi Akiva, poor also...
I mean he was.
Right, that's a good point. Right, that's a good point. Right, right.
ומעשה, U'maaseh, there's such a great story. There's a story, ומעשה באחד
שפרע ראש אשה בשוק, v'maaseh b'echad shepara rosh isha bashuk, he uncovered
the hair of a woman in the marketplace. באת לפני רבי עקיבא,
Bas lifnei Rabbi Akiva, so she came to רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva
for דין תורה. din Torah. וחייבו ליתן לו ארבע מאות זוז, V'chiyavo
lites lo arba meos zuz, like the משנה Mishnah says, 400 זוז.
zuz. אמר לו רבי, Amar lo Rebbi, אמר לו, amar lo, so
the litigant said, רבי תן לי זמן, Rebbi ten li zman, give
me a week to pay her. נתן לו זמן, Nasan lo zman,
fine you have a week. שמר אותה, Shamar osa, so he watched
her, עומדת על הפתח, omedes al hapesach, one day where she was
like by the door's, you know, the front of her door, בפתח
חצרה, b'pesach chatzeira, excuse me, the opening of the yard, and the
yard would open into the public domain, the רשות הרבים. reshus harabim.
ושבר את הכד בפניה, V'shavar es hakad b'faneha, so he was walking
down the street and he did a little device, you know, you
ever know on the TV shows where they have the person coming
in and testifying about what... and somebody drops and they look behind
them? Yeah, yeah, in the middle of the court the person doesn't
have whiplash? So it's something like this. So he's walking behind and
he drops a little, a little like vial of oil, right, you
know, in front of her in the רשות הרבים, reshut harabim, and
she's there by her jars. So what does she do?
So,
ושבר את הכד בפניה, v'shavar et hakad b'faneha, וכאיסר שמן, v'kh'issar shemen,
there was like a dollar's worth of oil in it.
וגלתה ראשה, v'giltah roshah, she took off the covering of her hair,
וספחה ושמה ידה על ראשה, v'saphcha v'samah yadah al roshah,
so she took the oil, look here's an opportunity to oil my
hair, right? So apparently that's something they would do. So she wasn't
concerned about exposing her hair in public if it gave her an
opportunity, she wanted the oil. She wanted the oil for her hair,
exactly. So she was willing to uncover her own hair to get
a dollar's worth of oil. Okay, הביא עליה עדים, hevi aleha edim,
he had witnesses see this. ובא לפני רבי עקיבא, u'va lifnei Rabbi
Akiva, אמר לו, amar lo, לזו אני נותן ארבע מאות
זוז? l'zo ani noten arba me'ot zuz? To this type of a
woman I'm going to give four hundred zuz for exposing her hair,
she was willing to do it for a dollar's worth of oil?
אמר לו, amar lo, לא אמרת כלום. lo amarta klum. He said
that's meaningless. החובל בעצמו, ha'chovel b'atzmo, אף על פי שאינו
רשאי, af al pi she'eino rashai, פטור, patur, and a person injures
himself, he's not allowed, but there's no payment. אחרים שחבלו בו חייבים,
acherim she'chavlu bo chayavim, others who injure him have to
pay. הקוצץ נטיעותיו, ha'kotzetz netiotav, אף על פי שאינו רשאי, af al
pi she'eino rashai, פטור, patur, there's no payment. אחרים שחבלו בו חייבים,
acherim she'chavlu bo chayavim, others are liable. She, it's true, she did
something stupid, she shamed herself, but the objective value of that shaming
is four hundred zuz, even though she was willing to do it
for one zuz. Okay, so therefore the fact that she was willing
to do it doesn't change the objective value of that shaming. Now
Rabbi Akiva's counter-argument is not so good because I mean, or whatever,
it's different because his point is that's different, there there's an objective
injury, right, to the body that you did to yourself that's worth
and you know, whereas here she doesn't consider this an embarrassment. But
that was exactly Rabbi Akiva's point. No, I don't care whether she
considers it an embarrassment or not, objectively I'm saying the same way
there's an objective injury to the body, if somebody's arm is cut
off that's an objective reality whether the person did it to themselves
or somebody else did it. There's an objective reality that we're all
from the upper class, even those of us, even people who are
willing to act in this way, ultimately there's an objective. Now that
also makes a high sense of responsibility. If you see yourself as
always from the upper class because of your heritage of אברהם יצחק
ויעקב, Avraham Yitzchak v'Yaakov, you always have to like, you know, act
to represent that. The flip side I'll just say of Rabbi Akiva
seems to be, by the way, not only raising the fact that
everybody, no matter how poor they are, is seen as part of
the upper class and has this minimum, but it also lowers people
that really do have wealth. He seems to be saying everybody is
like poor upper class. Okay, money is not what matters, we all
have equal dignity and status.
Yes, Mike. Yeah, you could consider it a different way. In other
words, what,
someone ripping off your clothes is different than if you're taking off
your robe to go into the shower, you know what I mean,
in a naked way, but like, you
know, depends on how that's.
That's an interesting point, that the act of shaming is not just
the objective reality, it's having it done to you.
Right, right, that's an interesting point. Like if I've got a little
stain here and I spit on it and I rub it off,
that's a little different than you spitting on it. Right, good point.
Yeah, and
this is a very modern attitude that we don't find often in
Torah from two thousand years ago, that is, a person himself is
not liable for his own degradation. He has a right to degrade
himself, but someone else can't do that.
Right, right. Actually, this reminds me of an interesting debate of Rabbi
Akiva and Ben Azzai because you know Rabbi Akiva says ואהבת לרעך
כמוך זה כלל גדול בתורה, v'ahavta l'reacha kamocha zeh klal gadol baTorah,
and Ben Azzai says no, זה ספר תולדות אדם זה כלל גדול
מזה. zeh sefer toldot Adam zeh klal gadol mizeh. So why, how's
Ben Azzai arguing? So you would think Ben Azzai is the universalist,
it's not just רעך, reacha, it's בן אדם, ben Adam, right, זה
ספר תולדות אדם, zeh sefer toldot Adam, everybody is a human being.
That is part, could be part of what he's saying, but actually
the Medrash goes on and he says because he says, you know,
if you're willing to treat yourself in a lowly fashion, okay, that
doesn't give you a right to treat somebody else that way. So
he's basically saying to Rabbi Akiva, ואהבת לרעך כמוך v'ahavta l'reacha kamocha
would only work if I take care of myself and I respect
myself. But if you don't respect yourself, it doesn't matter, you still
have to respect the other person. Right, that's what Ben Azzai is
saying back. But you know, it's interesting because Rabbi Akiva here is
talking about people that don't respect themselves, you know, and he even
says it doesn't matter, that doesn't really change the respect that they
are deserved that they deserve towards themselves. So it's interesting to read
this in the context of that.
Also, this happened in the שוק, shuk, that's like the worst place
that you could... Right, exactly. And the other one happened in the...
No, I think that's why it says בפתח החצר, b'phetach hachatzer, because
his, I think the street and the רשות הרבים reshut harabim was
going in front of her. Oh, the שוק shuk is still... It
is still true, a שוק shuk is different than just the street.
The שוק shuk is like everybody is gathering. Okay. איבעיא להו, ibaia
lehu, the גמרא Gemara says they raise
a
question, מנה צורי תנן. mana Tzori tnan. or
מנה מדינה, Maneh Medina, which is one-eighth of that value. All right,
and the same would be true when we say a סלע. Sela.
Okay, normally we're talking about מנה צורי Maneh Tzori when we say
a זוז Zuz and so on, but the question always is, like,
you know, to determine that is a huge question. Is it a
very large value or an eighth of that? תא שמע, Ta Shma,
come here. ההוא דתקע ליה לחבריה, Hahu d'tkala l'chavrei, somebody hit the
ear of his friend. He came before רבי יהודה נשיאה, Rabbi Yehuda
Nesia, the grandson of רבי יהודה הנשיא. Rabbi Yehuda HaNasi. אמר ליה,
Amar lei, said to him, הא אנא והא רבי יוסי הגלילי. Ha
ana v'ha Rabbi Yose HaGlili. Here am I, here's רבי יוסי הגלילי.
Rabbi Yose HaGlili. Remember what רבי יוסי הגלילי Rabbi Yose HaGlili said?
He said, how much did רבי יוסי הגלילי Rabbi Yose HaGlili say?
A מנה Maneh in the משנה Mishna for hitting a guy in
the ear. ומהא, V'ha, here am I and here is רבי יוסי
הגלילי, Rabbi Yose HaGlili, and therefore
הב ליה מנה צורי, Hav lei Maneh Tzori, give him a מנה
צורי. Maneh Tzori. So you see that he's interpreting the משנה Mishna
in רבי יוסי הגלילי Rabbi Yose HaGlili as a מנה צורי, Maneh
Tzori, the larger coinage. שמע מינה מנה צורי תנן שמע מינה. Shma
mina Maneh Tzori tnan shma mina. All right, that's a good proof.
He said explicitly מנה צורי, Maneh Tzori, that covers that, which means
a very high amount. Okay, מאי הא אנא והא רבי יוסי הגלילי?
Mai ha ana v'ha Rabbi Yose HaGlili? What does it mean here's
me, here's רבי יוסי הגלילי? Rabbi Yose HaGlili? אילימא הכי קאמר ליה,
Ilima hachi ka amar lei, here's what he means: הא אנא דחזיתך,
Ha ana d'chazitach, I saw you do
it, and רבי יוסי הגלילי, Rabbi Yose HaGlili, who said it's a
מנה צורי, Maneh Tzori, so you combine my testimony with רבי יוסי
הגלילי's Rabbi Yose HaGlili דין Din and you have to give him
a
מנה צורי. Maneh Tzori. One minute, it's not so clear you can
do that.
The גמרא Gemara says למימרא דעד נעשה דיין? L'meimra d'eid na'aseh dayan?
That means that if you see something, you, the person who was
the witness, could also turn around and be the judge? Right? Witness,
judge, and jury. As they say, prosecutor, judge, and jury. Anyway, so
can the person who actually serves as a witness also serve as
a judge? Okay, והתניא, V'hatanya, we
learned a ברייתא, Baraita, סנהדרין שראו אחד שהרג את הנפש, Sanhedrin sherau
echad sheharag et hanefesh, the סנהדרין Sanhedrin was going on a lunch
break, taking a walk down the street, and they saw a murder
take place. Okay, so how are they going to deal with it?
מקצתן נעשו עדים ומקצתן נעשו דיינים דברי רבי טרפון. Miktzatan na'asu eidim
umiktzatan na'asu dayanim divrei Rabbi Tarfon. רבי טרפון Rabbi Tarfon says
you can't both be witness and judge. Some of you have to
decide you're going to be the witnesses, the rest of you serve
as the דיינים. Dayanim. רבי עקיבא אומר, Rabbi Akiva omer, רבי עקיבא
Rabbi Akiva says, כולם עדים הם ואין עד נעשה דיין. Kulam eidim
hein v'ein eid na'aseh dayan. רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva says no, if
you saw something, even if you're not going to testify about it
in court, the very fact that you saw it means you have
to refuse yourself as a judge. Okay, so even as תוספות Tosafot
distinguishes between עד הרואה Eid HaRo'eh and
עד המעיד, Eid HaMei'id, so רבי עקיבא Rabbi Akiva says just seeing
you
invalidates you from the סנהדרין Sanhedrin in this case, where it's like
what, do they have standbys? Yeah, they can convene a
different סנהדרין Sanhedrin or something.
They only need twenty-three, they
don't need seventy-one. Okay, anyway, right, you only need twenty-three, you don't
need seventy-one. Okay, so the גמרא Gemara says, one minute,
עד כאן לא קאמר רבי טרפון, Ad kan lo ka amar Rabbi
Tarfon, when does רבי טרפון Rabbi Tarfon say they can't serve as
witnesses? מקצתן נעשו עדים ומקצתן נעשו דיינים. Miktzatan na'asu eidim umiktzatan na'asu
dayanim. He says the seeing doesn't invalidate them, but those that serve
as witnesses, actually are עד המעיד, Eid HaMei'id, they can't serve as
דיינים. Dayanim. Okay, you either have to take one role or the
other. אבל עד נעשה דיין לא קאמר, Aval eid na'aseh dayan lo
ka amar, he doesn't say that the very person who is the
judge can base the פסק, Psak, give the דין Din based on
his own testimony, what he himself saw. So the גמרא Gemara says,
how could this work? So the גמרא Gemara says, no, כי תניא
היא, Ki tanya hi, here's how it
works: כגון שראו בלילה, Kegon sherau balayla, if they saw it at
night, דלאו לבי דינא נינהו, D'lav l'vei dina ninhu, because you can't
hold a court case at night. So basically what it's saying is
like this: if I am the judge and I saw something, seeing
something directly, although now we know that eyewitness testimony is like highly
unreliable, but the point is, but then it's also unreliable when it
comes through witnesses. So seeing something directly is no worse than hearing
witness's testimony about it, which makes a lot of sense. Okay, although
maybe not, maybe you're too emotionally involved, you're not objective, and that's
some of the issues. Okay, but the גמרא Gemara is saying it's
possible you could see it and that would be like accepting the
testimony, you're seeing it yourself, and then you'll be the judge of
it. But it only works if you saw it in the daytime,
because testimony can only be received in court during the daytime. Okay,
so if you were walking down with your בית דין Beis Din
of twenty-three in the daytime and you saw a murder, it's like
you just saw somebody testify a murder to you and you can
פסקן Pasken about it. Okay, and in this case about the guy
who hit the ear, and he says, "I saw you," it's "Oh,
I saw you during the day." That's like I accepted testimony about
it. But this is a good advice, if you have to do
a crime, do it at night. Okay, but if you do it
at night, okay, then it's not like you can be like you
accepted testimony, so you have to wait till the next morning, and
then some people have to act formally as witnesses. you haven't yet
received the testimony, and then once they're acting as witnesses, they can't
turn around and act as judges. Okay, so the גמרא Gemara says
like this.
It's like that takes place at night. Right. Okay, כגון דלא לימדו
מיניה. k'gon d'lo limdu minei. ואי בעית אימא, ve'i ba'it eima,
so that's one answer. Okay, yes, he saw it but he saw
it during the day and that's like he received testimony during the
day. ואי בעית אימא, ve'i ba'it eima, הכי קאמר ליה. hachi ka'amar
leh. No, maybe he means something different. He didn't mean I saw
you. Here's what he meant. הא אנא דסבירא לי כרבי יוסי הגלילי.
ha ana d'svira li k'Rabbi Yose HaGlili. That's probably what we would
have assumed he meant. I hold like Rabbi Yose HaGlili דאמר מנה
צורי. d'amar maneh tzori. Here's me, I hold like Rabbi Yose HaGlili
who says a maneh tzori, והא סהדי דמסהדי בך veha sahadi d'mesahadei
bach and there are witnesses that testify against you. So we weren't
talking that he was the witness. There are witnesses. He's just saying
I'm the דיין dayan here and I hold like Rabbi Yose HaGlili.
הב ליה מנה צורי. hav leh maneh tzori. Okay, so now we're
going to wrap up this discussion of עד נעשה דיין. ed na'aseh
dayan. וסבר רבי עקיבא דאין עד נעשה דיין? vesavar Rabbi Akiva d'ein
ed na'aseh dayan? Does Rabbi Akiva really say that just by seeing
something you have to recuse yourself as a judge? והתניא? vehatanya? וכי
יכה איש את רעהו באבן או באגרוף. vechi yakeh ish et re'ehu
b'even o b'egrof. And it says ולא ימות ונפל למשכב, velo yamut
venaful l'mishkav, he doesn't die, so whatever then you have to pay,
רק שבתו יתן ורפא ירפא. rak shivto yitein verafo yerape. שמעון התימני
אומר Shimon HaTeimani omer מה אגרוף מיוחד שמסור לעדה ולעדים, mah egrof
meyuchad shemasur l'eidah ule'edim, the same way your fist can be looked
at? It says by a stone or a fist. That your stone
could be looked at by עדה. eidah. עדה Eidah
is the community, means the judges and
by
the witnesses. Both the witnesses and the judges can assess whether your
fist was had enough
power to do this type of injury. Whether it's considered that you
are to be fully blamed for the injury that was caused. So
to him it had to be assessed by the witnesses and the
judges. אף כל שמסור לעדה ולעדים. af kol shemasur l'eidah ule'edim. So
this would be true about any murder instrument
or implement used for creating
injury. It has to be assessed by the witnesses and the judges.
פרט שיצא מתחת יד העדים. perat sheyatza mitachat yad ha'edim. If the
עדים edim lost the murder instrument or they lost the or the
instrument that was used to inflict injury and then even if they
can testify, yes, it was an instrument that we should have known
would have inflicted this injury etc. etc., if the judges can't see
it and assess for themselves, he says the guy gets off. Okay,
so it's a very interesting הלכה. halacha. You need the judges to
be able to assess the instrument that was used for injury or
murder.
I don't understand what that means. They assess what the fist? How
do you know, like the judges can't necessarily assess oh I saw
it at this velocity?
So yeah, so take a look. Excellent, you've anticipated Rabbi Akiva. אמר
לו רבי עקיבא. amar lo Rabbi Akiva. Rabbi Akiva said to him
וכי בפני בית דין הכה? vechi bifnei beit din hikah? I don't
get it. So בית דין beit din can look at his fist
but בית דין beit din didn't see him hit him. It wasn't
seen in front of בית דין beit din שיודעים כמה הכה, sheyod'im
kamah hikah, how many times he hit him, ועל מה הכה, ve'al
mah hikah,
on what he hit him, what part of the body he hit
him at, אם על שוקו או על ציפור נפשו, im al shoko
o al tzipor nafsho,
was it by his thigh or was it by his, actually שוק
shok is a calf, or was it ציפור נפש tzipor nefesh is
some place I think like a temple or some place that's very
subject to injury. ועוד, ve'od, הרי שדחפו מחברו מראש הבירה, harei shed'chapo
mechavero merosh habirah, what if somebody pushed his friend off of the
top of the building, או מראש הבירה, o merosh habirah, from the
top of a castle, ומת, vamet, and he died, and we want
to determine was this something that normally would have led to death?
So if the בית דין beit din has to see this themselves,
what are you going to do? בית דין הולכין אצל הבירה, beit
din holchin etzel habirah, should they go on a field trip and
have to go look at this castle to see it by themselves?
או הבירה הולכת אצל בית דין, o habirah holechet etzel beit din,
let's
move the castle into the court? ועוד אם נפלה הבירה, ve'od im
naflah habirah, what if the castle fell down? חוזר ובונה את הבירה,
chozer uvoneh et habirah, rebuild the building so we can assess whether
it would have killed the guy? So clearly you cannot demand that
the בית דין beit din has to directly witness this stuff. There's
no way they're going to be able to directly witness whether this
and they have to rely on the עדים. edim. אלא מה אגרוף
מיוחד
שמסור לעדים.
ela mah egrof meyuchad shemasur
le'edim. No, an אגרוף egrof can be assessed by the witnesses. That's
all you need. You don't need the בית דין beit din to
assess, you just need the witnesses to assess.
אף כל שמסור לעדים. af kol shemasur le'edim. Anything that can be
assessed by the witnesses.
פרט שיצא
אבן מתחת ידו של מכה, perat sheyatza even mitachat yado shel makeh,
right? המכה hamakeh would be the smiter. Right, the
מכה *makeh*, the
smiter, right, the מכה *makeh*. Right, okay. And they
didn't have a good visual at the time.
And they
didn't have
a good visual at
the
time. Okay. קתני *Katani*, now why is any of this relevant? It's
a fascinating discussion, but why is any of this relevant to us?
קתני מיהת אמרו לו לרבי עקיבא וכי בפני בית דין היכה
שיודעים
כמה היכה *Katani miyat amru lo
le-Rabbi Akiva ve-chi bifnei Beis Din hika she-yode'in kama hika*?
And
Rabbi Akiva says did they do it in front of בית דין
*Beis Din*? בית דין *Beis Din* would be able to see what
they did, but you know what that suggests? היכה בפניהם עד נעשה
דיין *Hika bifneihem ed na'aseh dayan*. It suggests that if they had
directly seen the event, they could have used that as evidence. But
doesn't Rabbi Akiva say that as soon as they see something, they
have to recuse themselves? So there's an obvious answer. אליבא דרבי שמעון
התימני קאמרי ליה ולא סבירא ליה *Aliba de-Rabbi Shimon Ha-Temani ka'amrei leih
ve-lo sevira lei*. No, he's just making an argument from within your
point of view. Let me show you the absurdity of your argument.
I don't hold that a בית דין *Beis Din* witnessing anything can
ever be a judge. As soon as you get involved in being
a witness, you have to recuse yourself of being a judge, but
you that say the בית דין *Beis Din* has to be part
of seeing it, there's no way they can see the specifics of
the case. Okay, so let's continue on.
What about different scenarios of עד רואה עד מעיד *ed ro'eh ed
me'id*, when עד נעשה דיין *ed na'aseh dayan*, when not? Okay, let's
take a look now because now that we talked about having to
see the murder instrument or the instrument of injury, we're going to
turn to that as a practical case.
תנו רבנן *Tanu rabanan*. שור תם שהמית והזיק *Shor tam she-hemit ve-hizik*.
So it both murdered and this ox, so it's going to be
a שור הנסקל *Shor HaNiskal* but there's no payment right for a
שור *Shor* that killed. But they also did damage.
Okay, now, later, afterwards. Okay, now, remember, how does a שור תם
*Shor tam* pay? From the body of the ox. If you make
it into a שור הנסקל *Shor HaNiskal*, the guy who was damaged
is not going to have anything to collect from because it's going
to be אסור בהנאה *assur be-hana'ah*. So what do you do? דנין
אותו דיני נפשות ואין דנין אותו דיני ממונות *Danin oto dinei nefashot
ve-ein danin oto dinei mammonot*.
You have to make it a שור הנסקל *Shor HaNiskal*, not דיני
ממונות *dinei mammonot*, the guy sadly is going to be out. Was
that because that's the order? Would have been ממונות *mammonot* first?
It's not clear. That's a good question. מועד שהמית והזיק *Mu'ad she-hemit
ve-hizik*. Now let's say it was an ox that was a מועד
*Mu'ad* that the owner just pays cash. So in that case, דנין
אותו דיני ממונות וחוזרים ודנין אותו דיני נפשות *Danin oto dinei mammonot
ve-chozrin ve-danin oto dinei nefashot*. You first do the דיני ממונות *dinei
mammonot* judgment and then the דיני נפשות *dinei nefashot*. Now, it's not
clear why you have to care about that order. Have a שור
הנסקל *Shor HaNiskal* court case, and then you have a different court
case where the owner pays cash out of the pocket. קדמו ודנוהו
דיני נפשות *Kadmu ve-danuhu dinei nefashot*, if you did the דיני נפשות
*dinei nefashot* first, אין חוזרים ודנין אותו דיני ממונות *ein chozrin ve-danin
oto dinei mammonot*. Now why does that make sense? So Michael asked
a question about the תם *tam* with the order make a difference
they were תם *tam*, but we're going to focus on the מועד
*mu'ad*. Why does the order matter for the מועד *mu'ad*? So what
if he became a שור הנסקל *Shor HaNiskal*? Let's have our court
case and let the owner pay cash out of pocket for the
נזק *nezek*. So the גמרא *Gemara* says: וכי קדמו ודנוהו דיני נפשות
מאי הוי *ve-chi kadmu ve-danuhu dinei nefashot mai havei*? Big deal if
they did the דיני נפשות *dinei nefashot* first and made him a
שור הנסקל *Shor HaNiskal*. ליהדר ולידייניה דינא דממונא *li-hedar ve-li-dayniyah dina de-mammona*.
Let's have the case about him being a שור המזיק *Shor HaMazik*
and let the owner pay cash. So אמר רבא Rava אשכחתינהו לרבנן
דבי רב *amar Rava ashkachtinhu le-rabanan de-bei Rav*. I found the Rabbis
of the yeshiva of Rav. דיתבי וקאמרי *de-yatvi ve-ka'amrei*, and they were
sitting and saying the following, or just my דבי רב *de-bei Rav*
just means basically not from Rav necessarily, Rav was too whatever was
too early, meaning I found the Rabbis of the בית מדרש *Beis
Medrash* that they were sitting and saying the following thing. הא מני
רבי שמעון התימני היא *Ha manni Rabbi Shimon Ha-Temani hi*. This is
Rabbi Shimon Ha-Temani. דאמר מה אגרוף מיוחד שמסור לעדה ולעדים *de-amar mah
egrof meyuchad she-masur le-edah u-le-edim*. You have to see the murder weapon
and you have to see the weapon of injury. So big deal?
אלמא בעינן אומדנא דבית דין *alma ba'inan umdana de-veis din*. You need
the בית דין *Beis Din* to assess whether the object has the
power to do the thing that it did. Okay, so what's here
is the object of injury? The ox. So בית דין *Beis Din*
would have to assess the ox whether the ox had the capability
of inflicting the injury that it did under normal circumstances. והא כיון
דגמרוהו לדיניה לקטלא *ve-ha keivan de-gamruhu le-dineih le-katla*. Once it became a
שור הנסקל *Shor HaNiskal*, לא משגחינן ביה לאומדנא דבית דין *lo mashghinan
beih le-umdana de-veis din*. We don't say, okay, we paskin it's a
שור הנסקל *Shor HaNiskal*, oh, wait, we have to wait a week
for the next court case of נזק *nezek* and בית דין *Beis
Din* don't kill the ox yet, בית דין *Beis Din* will have
to inspect the ox directly to determine if it had the ability
to inflict the injury that it did. No, you're not allowed to
do that because you are postponing the execution, and this is so
fascinating. We went through all of בבא קמא *Bava Kamma* about that
you have to process the שור הנסקל *Shor HaNiskal* as if that
you would the owner was, you know, the murderer and had all
those requirements. Here we find that the same way if a person's
convicted of murder, of a capital crime, you don't delay the execution
because that is considered as like, you know, subjecting them to too
much anguish because they know they're going to die and they have
to be waiting all this time, you also don't do it for
the ox. Once you made the ox a שור הנסקל *Shor HaNiskal*,
you can't wait, we have to execute it right away. It's not
fair to the ox to wait too long.
Is that the issue or is the issue once convicted as a
שור הנסקל *Shor HaNiskal* it has no value?
No, but as a מועד *Mu'ad* you pay out of cash.
That's what. So לאומדנא דבית דין ולא מענינן לדיניה *le-umdana de-veis din
ve-lo ma'aninan le-dineih* and we don't. cause עינוי הדין an affliction of
the justice by having this poor ox have to wait until he
gets executed. So that's their explanation. Very nice explanation. We will see
tomorrow what רבא says back to express to respond to this explanation.